Hi . I 'll be your host for this commentary .
My name is Masato Kobayashi . I 'm a film writer .
Let me introduce our guests :
he director , Takashi Mike , and the screenwriter , Daisuke Tengan .
Hi .
Should I say " Nice to meet you " or " Good evening " ?
I 'm guessing most people won 't be watching this during the daytime .
- Good evening . I 'm Miike . - Hi , Tengan here .
This year marks the 10th anniversary of Audition .
Many of Mike 's films have been successful abroad ,
but Audition is especially popular .
This film has influenced horror writers all over the world .
In 2007 , Time magazine named Audition
one of the top 25 scariest horror movies ,
alongside the likes of Halloween ,
The Texas Chain Saw Massacre , and Bambi .
How did you feel about that ?
Well ...
I didn 't make this film to compete at international festivals
or to make money overseas .
I just wanted to do the best job I could do
while staying under budget
and still getting some enjoyment out of the filmmaking process ,
so it makes me very happy
for the film to get such recognition .
I feel like I 'm Yoji Takita with his movie Departures .
Well , they probably won 't know what I 'm talking about .
That 's a timely topic !
You know , it 's been a while .
And I 've been drinking a lot lately ,
so you 're going to have to forgive me if I remember things incorrectly
or if I get something wrong .
- Looking forward to that . - Okay .
Tengan , how do you feel about the film 's success ?
As I recall , when I accepted the job ,
there were a lot of Japanese horror movies being made .
I remember Miike told me that there was no sense in making another one .
I think that horror movies are generally done
by filmmakers who genuinely love horror movies
and who specialise in making horror movies .
Neither of us specialised in horror movies ,
so we knew right away that we 'd have a different approach .
As a result ...
I was chosen for Masters of Horror .
And again , we wanted Tengan to write . We didn 't want anyone else .
Even for this genre , we wanted Tengan .
And I don 't specialise in horror movies .
Oh , yeah , I 'm going to ask you about Imprint later .
Well ...
The original story was by Ryu Murakami .
You adapted his book to film .
Did you know the story before you started production ?
I had heard of it .
I had not read it yet .
Yeah , me neither .
So how and when did this all get started ?
Well ...
There 's this company , Omega Project . It 's a unique company .
And there was this guy , Yokohama .
He wasn 't in the film industry .
He started this company
as a way of making money .
And this was a so-called " independent film . "
He liked the novel .
He thought the story was interesting , and he thought it 'd be a good movie .
So , he teamed up with Shindo , our producer .
They talked to Murakami , and they got the green light from him .
They discussed who they thought would be best suited to direct .
I think that 's how it started .
So , we weren 't the ones who brought in the story .
How was the original book adapted for the film ?
I think it 's close to the original story .
At least in the first half , it 's very close to the original story .
You did a good job at making it feel more faithful than it is , Tengan .
Right , right .
In the beginning , Murakami had a lot of ideas ,
a lot of opinions about how it should be made .
Since it 's his story , it 's his baby , but also because he 's a director , too ,
so I pretended to listen .
When we finished the film , we brought it to Murakami .
Right when it was completed , there was a screening for Murakami only .
We weren 't even there .
But just after the screening , he called me , and he was very excited .
He said , " This is awesome . This is great ! "
Apparently , he liked the scenes we changed from the original story .
I got the idea that he was willing to trust other people
to turn his story to a movie .
But the basic story was well-written . We put that into the script .
When you think about it , all we really had to do
was add actors and sets to the equation , make it real .
That 's how we made this film .
Of all the movies I 've made ,
very few of them stick so closely to the script ,
but this was one of them .
Some scenes toward the end did end up
being different from the original story .
I used some more cinematic plots .
It is pretty different from your typical horror movie ...
but I think that 's what made it interesting .
So , do you not consider Audition to be " horror " ?
Well , usually horror movies deal with ...
something supernatural or demonic or whatever .
So , how do I put this ?
People get spooked by that .
They shake in fear .
From my point of view , humans are much scarier .
Humans can be demons or angels .
So , in this movie ...
well ...
all the characters in this are just regular folks ,
but regular folks have dark sides ,
and here those dark sides are portrayed in kind of a bizarre way .
Aoyama ends up like he does , and he is responsible for that .
One common theme among these characters
is that they just want to be happy .
Usually Japanese horror movies
are based on old Japanese legends and scary stories called kaiaan .
It 's always about grudges , resentment , that kind of thing .
Sorrow , you know ...
Jealousy , sometimes .
So , dead people become these spirits of vengeance ,
and they terrorise the people who are still alive .
Now , I don 't know that I would know how to direct that kind of movie .
I don 't necessarily want to make a movie with that kind of story .
And of course , like we said ,
it didn 't feel like we were making a horror movie .
Yeah , how should I put it ?
Murakami 's original story was about trauma ,
and it seemed to be more of a psychological suspense ,
so this movie was developed with that kind of genre in mind .
I think when people go over the edge , they get totally messed up .
That 's normal . That 's human nature .
And what 's happening isn 't always clear , but using a movie to show that is easier .
We can mix up many things .
Here 's my take on it .
I think that Murakami experienced , in his life ,
a fear similar to what Aoyama ,
played by Ryo Ishibashi , was feeling .
He was making many films at that time , and had many auditions .
In those auditions , I don 't think he met anyone like Asami ,
but he probably met someone ,
and in meeting that person , something strange happened .
I felt like this story could be a personal message to that person .
The message might be " I still love you . "
Pretty unfair form of communication , by the way .
But maybe that 's why it doesn 't seem like fiction .
The original story seems to be written by a writer
who has experienced something like this .
Since Murakami didn 't originally come from the film industry ,
I think that when he got involved in directing and making movies ,
he must have found some things very interesting , even strange .
Like auditions . We do auditions ; that 's what we do .
But from his point of view , he was probably like ,
" Oh , she 's sexy , " and she 's going , " What ? Really ? "
And when he starts wondering why someone would come to that audition ,
that can evolve into a really scary story .
Maybe he did something to someone . We don 't know .
As a writer , he probably saw something
that he found really intriguing .
How was Murakami involved during production ?
Did he show up on the set , or ... ?
No , no . I only met him one time , actually .
We had a meeting and we talked about a lot of things .
He didn 't give me any detailed instructions .
I think he wanted to get a feel for who I was .
He 'd entrusted me with his story ; it 's only natural he 'd want to meet ,
but he didn 't give me any ultimatums or say that I couldn 't do this or that .
He was not that kind of person .
He 's onscreen now .
The main character was played by Ryo Ishibashi .
Ishibashi is also a musician .
He was in a number of Yakuza pictures before Audition , wasn 't he ?
What made you choose him for this role ?
That 's a difficult question .
Well ... we thought ...
It had to be a middle-aged man who was still pretty attractive .
Ten years ago , he looked like
a normal adult man ...
At least to us .
He looked like he was kind to women , and because of that ,
maybe he could be insecure or unhappy even though he 's sexually attractive .
We couldn 't think of anyone else besides Ishibashi .
What else ?
My intuition had told me
that he was hungry for something .
There weren 't many engaging roles in Japanese films at that time .
He was wondering what to do next .
I think he always had Yusaku Matsuda in his mind .
He wanted to be competing with him ,
but there were no good roles for him to compete with Matsuda .
So we thought ... if we can offer him a good movie ,
he could create his own world .
In the scenes toward the end ,
he gets all mangled up .
He can 't even move , and he just groans in pain .
It must have been so uncool for a rocker like him ,
but he wanted the part , he wanted to play it .
It felt right at the time .
How different was the character played by Ishibashi
from the character that Tengan had put in the script ?
It was close .
Like Mike said , he had 10 be sexually attractive .
And he looked indecisive .
In other words , even if he says , " This way , "
he could be thinking , " It may be that way . "
So he 's concerned . He doesn 't know what to do .
He has that kind of feeling .
And ...
his age and his looks matched the character perfectly .
I didn 't know him then .
When I saw him at the screening ,
I asked him to appear in my other movies .
It was because he had made such an impression in this film .
Do you like having auditions
for the films you direct ?
Do you do auditions a lot ?
You mean , like , regular auditions ?
Yes .
Do you ever just pick someone you don 't know to be in your movie ?
Yeah . I think that 's the basis for creating something new .
You might like the person .
It 's a gamble .
You can 't know everything from an audition .
But you can get a feeling .
You chose the person , it 's like trying your luck .
Or , you can insist that you got lucky ,
because you 'd already chosen them long ago .
So ...
But you can 't complain because you 're the one who made the choice .
And sometimes you can 't decide .
How about you , Miike ? Do you like having auditions ?
Yeah , I like them , but ...
when I 'm having an audition ,
I get this funny feeling , like I 'm actually imitating another audition .
In other words ...
I 'm just copying what I 've learned from older colleagues ,
so my auditions aren 't specifically " mine " .
So , these days , my assistant director will hold the auditions ,
which allows me to watch from the side and sort of be more objective .
And if I feel like asking or saying something , I will .
But when I think back , I 've definitely held auditions where ,
the moment the person comes through the door ,
I know they 're the one .
Yeah , me too .
That 's exactly how Aoyama felt in Audition .
He had this strong feeling just from looking at her picture .
So , when he sees her , his mind is already made up .
He asks some questions , but ...
it 's just confirming the feeling he had .
I think it 's very close to my experience .
You encounter someone who was born to play the role .
As soon as the person opens the door , you know that they 're the one .
I think that 's true of a lot of auditions .
How about the auditions for this film ?
That is , for Audition did anything like that happen ?
Do you remember ?
No . For this film , most of the actors were ...
Well , we thought about Asami 's role . We researched a lot .
And we met some people ,
but it wasn 't like an audition .
We already had someone in mind ,
but we thought that maybe that wouldn 't be fair ,
so we decided to see some actors .
For other parts , we sought out ...
unique actors to play certain roles .
This house we used as a set is located in Seijo .
No , it 's located in Denenchofu , an upscale residential area .
We made a surprise visit to this house , which is just owned by a regular family .
We asked them to let us use the house .
We put all the family members in an upstairs room for a few days .
We were filming till midnight .
It 's amazing they let us use the house .
Did you show up there without any notice ?
No , we actually took half a month to negotiate and get consent .
And since we used every room in the house ,
when we left , it was sort of like moving out .
So , you sort of lived on set .
It was a very Japanese way to shoot a movie .
We begged to rent this house from this family .
How did Dead or Alive and Audition influence your career ?
I mean , you used to make direct-to-video movies and genre films .
Now , you make films that are screened at international film festivals .
I think these two films must have given you an opportunity
to go in a new direction .
So , for you , Mike , would you say that 's accurate ,
that these two films had an impact on your life or your career ?
Well , aside from my personal feelings about those two movies ,
the fact is that Audition helped me a lot ,
and it happened at just the right time .
Yes , I directed this movie ,
but without the producers who wanted to make this film
or Murakami 's original story , it wouldn 't have happened .
Without Tengan 's screenplay , it wouldn 't have happened .
I once realised , " I see . "
I am a filmmaker , but it 's not as though
I made the film all by myself .
There were a series of encounters , and this film came along .
And because it did , a lot of things changed significantly .
It started in a small festival called Courmayeur .
From there , it was selected for the Rotterdam Film Festival .
I got an award .
Since I was used to those direct-to-video movies , the " V-Cinema " ,
film festivals were like ...
something from another planet .
So , I thought ...
I wasn 't worried about pleasing foreign audiences .
" If I keep on doing whatever I 'm doing in Japan ,
" people around the world will watch them . "
And that was a great thing .
Film is a very powerful medium .
So , this movie Is very important to me ,
but it 's difficult for me to get away from it .
I 'm currently working on a film that is considered " normal , "
so in Europe they 're going , " Miike is finished , "
and " The man who made Audition is gone . "
But that means that it had a huge impact , didn 't it ?
I think so . After Audition and Visitor O ,
Imprint , which was also written by Tengan , came along ,
and people started to consider me a horror movie director .
We just saw her picture on the screen a little while ago .
Shiina , the main actress , was in Tokyo Gore Police recently .
Right . She 's back . Yes .
She quit once because she had her heart broken .
I heard she was in Kyushu .
She came back and she 's doing good .
I see . So , she hadn 't been doing a lot of acting .
Yeah . Well ...
She doesn 't seem to be interested in living the life of an actress .
She 's had her good moments and her bad moments ,
and , you know ...
It 's not everything . It 's not the most important thing .
She started out as a model .
She was different from other actresses .
The feeling she gives this film wasn 't created from whole cloth .
It was kind of her true colour .
We wanted to bring that feeling , as it was , into the film .
That 's Eihi Shiina .
It 's difficult to create that kind of aura in acting .
We have to make up an episode for her .
There isn 't much information about her in the movie ,
but her presence itself just feels ominous and foreboding .
How about you , Tengan ?
Yeah , she 's very mysterious .
Wasn 't she in a Yukisada movie ? I saw her in something at a screening .
She was mysterious . We 're not sure if she 's like that normally .
And I think we didn 't really get to know her .
We wanted to keep our distance to keep that feeling as real as possible .
It feels like she has something inside that is disturbing .
Her natural tension just makes people feel that way .
I think that fit the film .
Now we 're seeing the audition scene of this film .
Who are these people ?
Some of them are young prospective actresses .
By the way , this lady is a staff member .
We improvised some of these , which made it like a real audition .
We just left the camera rolling and kept the good ones .
But I 'm not really very good at that kind of thing .
It could 've been better .
This scene is kind of sluggish .
But the sluggishness could be perceived as being very Japanese .
In Japan , once we say " Okay , " it 's difficult to do it again .
Back then , it was very difficult to check rushes and reshoot the scene .
You 're destined to make some mistakes .
Your film will have some mistakes .
Accept it and move on .
So , that brings some uncertainty and imperfections that were not planned ,
but the effect is mostly positive , I think .
If it was perfect , and it dictated the audience 's feeling ,
people would feel like it was too calculated and overdone ,
and I 'd guess it probably wouldn 't have been so popular .
It looks like you took a long time to shoot this scene .
It was just rolling .
There were no bloopers .
We would just call " Next ! " That 's all we did .
And there were people who were watching the audition .
They were waiting for their turn and watching on the side .
They watched the people performing .
They couldn 't figure out what to do . Some tried very hard .
Others were totally nervous .
There were no directions , so it was very realistic .
Even just looking at her back , I feel something scary .
She has something . I wonder how she is in real life .
We 're going to see some horrific stuff .
If we could see her ambition as an actress or something ,
we could understand what she wanted to do .
But she wasn 't like that . She was so mysterious .
We didn 't want to ruin the mystery ,
so we tried not to talk to her much .
We didn 't try to understand her , and she didn 't ask us anything .
That was our relationship .
Even 10 years later ,
I probably still don 't know who she is .
By the way , this scene is too long .
We wanted to show the audition going on and on and on
to show how long it took to finally get to her .
The title is Audition and this is the only audition scene .
I think these two male characters are totally opposite .
Kunimura is ...
How can I put this ?
Back then , he was already established , but he was an unusual type .
He wasn 't an actor everybody knew .
The pros knew who he was .
He was very cooperative .
He doesn 't have much ego , and he pays attention to what 's going on .
He thinks about how his character should be played
in relation to the other character , Aoyama , played by Ishibashi .
Of course , it was described in the script , but for example ,
he chooses his tone of voice based on the other actors .
It depended on how the others acted .
He is a wonderful actor for a director .
In this scene , she is wearing a white dress .
Does that mean something ?
It 's more of a suit .
Well ...
We wanted it as simple as possible .
It doesn 't show much pride .
At first glance , she looks like an open person .
But you can 't actually tell who she is .
We tried to use a simple costume for her .
It applies to her hairstyle and makeup . She had very little makeup on .
How old was she back then ?
Who ? Shiina ?
I think she was 23 or 24 .
Ishibashi is talking now .
She has an unusual face .
Let 's talk about Tengan 's career .
Okay .
You 've been involved In many movies as a writer ,
and you direct , too .
Can we talk about the films you directed ?
- The films I directed ? - Yeah .
I directed Aiki and Ishibashi was in that , too .
And I did Waiting in the Dark .
The Most Beautiful Night in the World hit the screens last year .
I 've done some documentaries , like Muteki no Handicap .
I 'm so twisted .
I 'm twisted .
Last year 's movie was so twisted .
- What do you think ? - I 'm a huge fan .
He 's not trying to please people .
I think , in Japan ,
there are very few people who make films like that .
It 's like it 's not his job .
It 's more like fate . He makes films because it 's his fate .
Meanwhile , we make films to make a living .
It 's the complete opposite .
What do you think ?
Maybe it 's not my job . Maybe it 's fate , like you say .
That 's the ideal .
If it were like that forever that 'd be great ,
but it can 't always be like that .
Did you like writing Audition ?
Yeah . I like writing screenplays .
So , I enjoy writing for myself and other people .
I really enjoy writing .
Is there a difference
between writing for yourself and writing for other directors ?
Recently , there has not been much difference .
But when I 've never worked with a particular director ,
since I don 't know the person very well ,
I 'll tend to write more details .
This was the first film that I worked on with Miike .
The whole time I was writing , I wondered how Miike would direct it .
The script was very detailed , so I had a lot of questions .
" What does that mean ? " " When did this happen ? "
But everything just had to be accepted .
I realised that maybe I didn 't have to understand everything .
You can 't always tell which scene is from whose point of view .
When I was reading this story ,
I thought everybody would share time with somebody ,
but each person probably has a totally individual perspective .
Three people are here right now , but we all see this moment differently ,
and things take on entirely different meanings from alternate points of view .
That 's the reality . When we fall in love and spend time together ,
we tend to think we share the same time and same kinds of feelings ,
but actually there are two thoroughly different worlds .
Each person has his or her own world .
And people forget to think of each other 's feelings , or world .
So , oddly ...
the sequence in the last half was actually kind of natural .
I wasn 't trying to make it eccentric .
I shot it in a natural way .
So , after Audition , as you guys told me ,
you worked together on Imprint for Showtime 's Masters of Horror .
I was criticised by so many people for that .
I was told to do whatever I wanted to do .
American producers watched Audition , and they liked it .
I was chosen for Masters of Horror - All big-name directors on the series .
And the 13th film , the last in the series , was mine .
I wondered why they chose mine for last .
I thought , " This is going to be so much fun . "
It was for cable TV , and they said I could do whatever I wanted .
America is a country of liberty . There is freedom of expression .
They told me to do something I couldn 't get away with in Japan .
So I did it , and they said , " That 's too much . "
They said , " We can 't air this on cable TV . "
In England , it was shown uncut ,
so it was still watched by a lot of people .
But I do think that putting Tengan and I together ...
IS dangerous for producers .
But we haven 't learned our lesson . He 's writing a story for me right now .
It 's going to be a serious , period-piece drama ,
and Tengan is writing the story .
- Is it 13 Assassins ? - Yes .
I think some folks in Toho may even pass out ...
when they learn what the story is about .
They don 't understand us .
It 's unbelievable .
Yeah , they 'll misunderstand . They 'll never get it .
So , are you allowed to talk about the story ?
It 's not that I 'm not allowed . It 's just that it 's unfinished .
We don 't even know where the story will end up yet .
I can understand distributors worrying . We need a big audience .
And it 's going to cost a lot ,
so if we don 't get a big audience
we will lose money , and I understand that .
But how do we want to entertain the audience ?
Maybe it 'll just be an okay film for people to come and have a good time ,
but that 's not what we 're after , that 's not what we 're shooting for .
We don 't find that kind of movie very attractive .
We 're not against that kind of thing ,
but if we 're being true to ourselves , the movie is going to be crazy .
There are landmines placed throughout the story .
It 's very exciting .
We 're going to set a new record for most people killed in a story .
The number is unbelievable .
It seems like no matter what I write , there are always characters left to Kill .
Just wait until you see it .
So , the screenplay is almost finished ?
Yes , almost .
Are you planning on shooting this year ?
Yes .
We are planning to show it at the Venice Film Festival next year .
That 's our goal .
Mike , you studied filmmaking at a school
founded by Tengan 's father , Shohei Imamura , right ?
Well , I went to school , but I 'm not sure if I studied or not !
I would like to ask about your relationship with Imamura .
Can you tell me about your work relationship ?
Or were you friends ?
Well , I was ...
before ... how do I put this ?
Imamura is surrounded by fascinating people ,
a lot of very unique folks .
And you go , " How did these people get involved in filmmaking ? "
I was working as an assistant director for TV shows .
My role was to make sure the production was on track .
The job and I were like oil and water .
I don 't think I 'm someone who should ever be an assistant director .
A person like me is not supposed to be there , at least usually .
But I guess I was useful in a way .
I don 't think Imamura was expecting much from me
as an assistant director .
I wasn 't Imamura 's understudy or anything like that .
The way they lived and worked was reflected in their movies .
It was about how your life became intertwined with filmmaking .
That was the big difference from other directors ,
and that 's not something I can duplicate .
So , I have to make films in my way and with my own voice .
I just have to do it in my own style .
That 's what I learned from him . In that sense , I 'm like him .
Doing something different from him was the way to go .
But I really regret that I wasn 't of much help to him .
He had this way of looking at me , like , " Why are you here ? "
So , did you guys know each other before this ?
Not really . We had only met once .
You might not remember this , but I met you at a New Year 's party .
Yeah , that 's right .
At that time ...
I had just started working for Imamura .
I see .
So , we knew each other but hadn 't yet had a conversation ,
and I got a call from him for this film .
I heard about him through Inagaki ,
who was working for Imamura as a set designer .
They were saying , " Daisuke Tengan Is a really thought-provoking guy . "
The people talking about Tengan 's productions really seemed to ...
enjoy feeling the pain .
I think they really felt like they were making something .
They seemed to have fun and enjoy the uniqueness .
It had obviously been a pleasant experience .
Is that accurate ?
Yeah , my productions are tough ,
but I think Miike 's productions are tough , too .
Yes , physically tough .
It 's the same thing .
We didn 't have a lot of time to shoot this , you know ?
How many days ?
How many days ? I don 't remember ...
but I think it was about three weeks .
Is that too short for you now ?
No , but back then , three weeks was one week longer than usual .
On most of my movies , I had to shoot everything in two weeks ,
and I got really used to working like that .
I knew how to direct in that kind of schedule .
As time went on , I 'd get more and more days to shoot .
If , all of a sudden , I get a whole three months ,
that would be a huge movie .
If we worked for three months
as intensely as we work on those two-week shoots , we 'd die .
So , having three months means we 'd work more leisurely .
We 'd have to make each day a good deal easier on everyone .
I didn 't know how to do that .
Far from it ,
my style was pushing everyone as much as I could , working hard ,
even when we were exhausted , and finishing in two or three weeks .
Tengan , what about you ? Was it always a battle against time ?
Yeah , it was like that for me , too .
Short and concentrated .
Even if we have a lot of days to shoot , it still feels very tight .
You have to struggle to keep your concentration .
I heard Tarantino talking about you .
He said Miike was the director who was making the most films .
And it 's true . You make a lot of movies .
What 's that like ? How are you able to do so many ?
Well , there are a lot of directors who are just constantly putting out films .
Directors of " Pink Films " in Japan , for instance , put out tons of stuff .
In Mexico , there are movies coming out all the time .
It was never my intention , really ,
to be known for making a lot of films .
But it 's kind of convenient .
Oh , that 's scary . The bag moved suddenly .
It just kind of happened .
I didn 't set out to make so many . It wasn 't part of some big scheme .
It just kind of happened that way .
After every movie , I always feel like I only have one movie left in me .
When I 'm shooting a longer picture ,
I think about making commercials or something on the side ,
just by using extra time , the crew and equipment are already there .
I don 't think it 's necessarily a good thing to make so many movies ...
but in Japan you can 't really make a living if you 're not shooting all the time .
I understand .
Ishibashi looked skinnier back then .
I think he 's a size bigger now . He looks very dignified .
He didn 't always have a lot of roles , but things have been happening .
He had always wanted ...
to work in Hollywood , to try something ...
he wanted to try something outside of Japan .
And if he wants to follow Matsuda 's example ,
he has to go abroad , and that 's what he 's been doing .
He 's been putting himself out there . He learned English .
Miike , did you go through any changes
during the shooting of this ?
Well ... how can I put this ?
Well ...
This was not the first one .
Even though it wasn 't a big production , I wanted to use film ,
and I wanted to make it for theatrical release .
Before this , I used film for promotion ,
to sell videos to the theatre audiences ,
theatrical films as promotion ,
so even though this wasn 't going to have a big budget ,
it was my intention for it to be seen theatrically .
It was really the first film that I made specifically for that format .
You used to make " V-Cinema " ,
but after Audition and Dead or Alive
your area was bigger , your audience was bigger .
You made bigger pictures ,
so you sort of went through three different arenas of film .
Now do you think about the budget or the genre
when you are considering a project
and thinking about which gig to accept ?
No . No .
Usually ... the way it usually goes ...
If I 'm not paying close enough attention , then it can really go any way .
But from the producers that I used to work with ,
to just the people I hung out with ,
some , obviously , have come and gone over the years ,
but others have kept plugging away .
Sometimes people will form a new company or something ,
and that might be a place where I can bring a project .
Time passes , and gradually ...
everyone who once worked together has scattered to different areas ,
and each person is working hard to make their own way .
But when they get the chance ,
sometimes they 'll think of me and give me a call .
This has happened time and time again with people I used to know .
Inevitably , my films are staffed with folks who 've all worked with me before .
I see .
My goal isn 't necessarily to get every person in the country to see it ,
but when a lot of people watch your movie
and you 're recognised in the industry ,
it 's easier to get a lot more freedom on these low-budget projects .
Casting becomes easier .
You don 't have to sacrifice quality .
So , I will keep on making films and meeting more people .
Look at stuff like genre movies or " Pink Films " ,
those can be made with very low budgets .
They don 't have to be huge movies .
I want to make interesting movies .
What are your plans for the future , Tengan ?
More directing ?
Well ...
My approach to filmmaking is a little different from Miike 's .
When a professional makes a film , it can be intriguing ,
but lately I 'm thinking that there are limits to what they can do .
I want to make something that is amateurish .
A pro makes movies as an occupation .
They don 't want anything in there to be unnecessary ,
but they lose something when they always work in that mind-set .
At least , that 's how I feel .
It 's kind of the opposite of how big movies are approached .
My roots are in independent film ,
and I think that 's the direction I want to return to now .
It 's difficult in Japan , because there aren 't as many producers .
I mean ...
I find something interesting and want to do it with these people ,
and we find some people to make it happen .
Then we get together and create something .
But the current producers in Japan are kind of all the same ; they 're trendy .
They say , when we edit , " It 's too long . "
And I think , " What 's wrong with being too long ? "
They say , " The pace isn 't good , " or " This line isn 't necessary . "
They don 't want anything unnecessary .
If the movie 's nothing but good stuff , I think that gets kind of boring .
They like big stars in the movies ,
and the big stars have to look cool .
And to make them look cool , they bring in other , less-cool actors .
It 's so unnatural .
People who try to resist that tendency ,
I think that 's a great quality to have .
That 's definitely something Tengan has .
It 's a weapon that you can use to shape your film .
In America , there are factors that create variety in filmmaking .
For example , we can 't tell if Steven Soderbergh is a pro or not .
Tarantino is totally an amateur ...
at least in that sense .
Can you explain that ?
He doesn 't know how to shoot .
Really ?
He knows what kind of shot he wants .
When I went to see the shooting of Grindhouse ,
he was having fun riding in the stunt car .
He was saying , " This is scary ! It 's so cooll "
And they just keep on going . They go on and on .
In that sense , he 's not trying to be a " professional " filmmaker .
And for the audience , that 's why he 's great ,
they keep that atmosphere and let him make whatever he wants .
They can still commercialise his films and make a lot of money .
But there are some people who are really proactive .
They challenge .
They want to be successful , even for just a short time , in Hollywood ,
rather than having a long and " safe " career somewhere else .
In Japan , there are no producers like that at all .
So , there are many , many films that come out that are all right ,
but they aren 't very interesting or challenging .
It 's extremely difficult for unique voices to compete in that environment .
Everybody has the same style .
They try to make it appear different by using more distinctive music ,
or fancy cutting or camera movements ,
and they may think that that stuff makes their films unique ,
but I don 't think so , it 's not about that .
So , I was lucky . Miike understood my story .
I wrote the story , but I was always wondering ,
" What are people going to think when they read this ? "
I wondered a little bit .
But I handed it over , turned it in .
I was so excited to meet him and get his reaction .
And he said it was good .
So ... that 's really how it all came together ,
and that made me really happy .
But even with Miike behind it ,
if other people had found it confusing or unclear ,
the movie wouldn 't have received the recognition that it has .
The audience wouldn 't have found it as interesting .
In Japan , it 's pretty difficult to make this kind of film .
What was it like when you made Imprint ?
We knew that might cause problems , but we did it anyway .
It was a shorter-form film called Imprint .
It was close to the original story .
I got the impression that they really wanted me to do something .
They 'd seen Audition overseas .
One good thing about Audition ,
you 'll never know the reason why the movie was made .
That 's the power of it .
For Imprint , we had direction . We knew why we were making it ...
so in that sense , it was easier to make .
That could have been our motivation ... for crossing the line .
I never thought about it like " crossing the line , " though .
Audition was so much scarier .
The story was realistic .
The original story was like that .
Imprint had a story that was kind of set in its own world .
It wasn 't that real-life kind of fear that you feel with Audition .
With Imprint , I think Miike took his enthusiasm to an extreme .
Hey , I just did what the script said to do .
This guy 's the dangerous one .
But it was impossible for American audiences
to understand killing an infant because of poverty ,
or getting an abortion or throwing a baby in the river .
They probably didn 't see any reason for there to be movie about that .
The reaction to Audition between Europe and America was very different .
In London and Paris , there were all these female reporters .
They said that I was a feminist .
They thought , " Hey , she 's getting revenge on these womanizers . "
In New York , I was told by male and female reporters that I was the devil .
I was like , " Really ? "
I wanted to say , " Asami is the devil in this , not me . "
Each country has its own reaction .
They have totally varied perspectives .
Audiences from Japan , Europe and America ,
they all had very particular responses to watching Imprint .
But Tobe Hooper , the director , told me ...
that when there was an announcement in the newspaper
that the film wouldn 't be aired on TV , that 's when I became a real director .
Which was very Tobe Hooper of him to say .
He is awesome .
Yeah , I 'm not sure if that makes me happy or not .
I felt like the plot 's development in this was covered up .
For example , you learn about Asami , but only little by little .
Her strangeness Is revealed very gradually .
It all happens very slowly .
Was that the plan when you were writing ?
Was that what you wanted ,
or did you guys have discussions about the pacing and things like that ?
In the original story ,
it doesn 't show how Asami lives or much of her background ,
but she says things that sound too peculiar to be true ,
and I really wanted to emphasize that aspect in the script .
And I think Miike had a vision of where he wanted to take it .
Yeah , as far as the plot , I left it up to him .
Whenever we 'd meet , I told him to do whatever he wanted to do .
He took the story where he wanted .
You know ...
a screenplay is kind of ...
its own art form ,
separate from the final film .
So it 's up to ... the writer .
In Japan , writers are appreciated for incorporating the opinions and ideas
of the producers and the directors ; not only is that appreciated , it 's expected .
They 're expected to listen to everybody 's opinions .
Of course , when you work that way ...
you have to actually use these ideas from all these other various people .
That 's why I wanted to leave him alone as much as possible .
When I read the story for the first time ...
except the last sequence ...
I thought that it would be relatively easy for me to shoot .
So , for the first hour ,
which is the first 60 pages in the script ,
everything 's pretty normal , there 's no jumping around in time .
As a movie , it 's explanatory , it 's very matter-of-fact ,
and it includes some scenes which could have been cut out
so the audience could get the impression
that this movie is not all it 's cracked up to be .
It was like , if the plot didn 't move forward enough in the next five minutes ,
some audiences would have walked out , and by then it 'd be too late to reach them .
So , it 's almost too late .
They spend the first hour thinking that the film is not what they heard about ,
getting more and more frustrated as it goes along ,
and then , suddenly , the plot develops in a crazy way .
So , I find the plot very uncommon .
But upon reading the story , I could imagine how to make it .
I knew how I should do it right when I read it .
So , I think that 's ...
that 's probably the biggest difference between the original story
and the plot of the screenplay .
What do you think ?
When I write ,
if the story belongs to a certain genre , such as psychological thriller ,
I would have the story develop at a faster pace for the first half .
Maybe put in more action scenes .
I 'd probably use more cinematic plots .
Once I realised this film wouldn 't be like that , I stopped writing .
I realised I might have been going in the wrong direction .
I left the script for two or three days .
I was just waiting for something to hit me .
Then the thought of playing with time occurred to me .
Even if the story goes back and forth in time ,
I thought the audience should still be able to follow it .
And since they were seeing it visually ,
it 'd be less confusing than it would be to read .
Because of CG technology , we can do anything now .
We can control space ,
so the audience isn 't going to be impressed , necessarily ,
regardless of what we do with time and space ; they 've seen it before .
But sitting in a theatre , you 're sharing time with others .
You 're forced to share that time .
So , I thought , if I could work on that , it could be intriguing .
That 's what I was thinking .
As Miike said before ,
we share time when we watch something , and sometimes it 's slow ,
and sometimes it 's fast , and I wanted to control how that felt .
I really wanted the audience to feel an acceleration of time in the last half .
That 's what I wanted to do .
Miike understood that and did his thing .
When I saw this film at a screening ...
I was impressed in a lot of ways .
The story was perfectly visualized .
When I write , it 's the world of imagination .
Here he is . Renji Ishibashi .
He 's kind of a toy in the Japanese film industry .
Everybody has fun playing with him . Just how to play is up to you .
He 'll tell you , " I 'm not your toy , " but he really does enjoy it .
As an actor , he knows what he 's doing .
He 's in several of my movies . I really love him .
Was this film the first thing you did with him ?
We did The Bird People in China .
He 'd say , " I 'm an actor who can handle the shooting ,
" even in remote areas , so don 't worry about it . "
But then he 'd start whining and going , " Do you know I was a child actor ? "
" I can 't handle this anymore . "
He was whining .
I thought that was hilarious .
I really wanted to put him In my movies .
He 's just an enthralling guy .
He 's like a vestige of an older Japanese film industry .
He worked with Shintaro Katsu all the time .
He missed him a lot . He wished Katsu was there .
Although I wasn 't a member
of any of the five major Japanese production companies
and I 've worked freely ,
when I come into contact with someone like him ,
it reminds me that the older generations are not irrelevant to us ,
nor are we to them .
He genuinely loves acting .
He had special makeup on that day .
No , it 's not that day . He had another scene .
He had some crazy makeup on for the scene .
And he had to wait for eight hours .
And there was another guy who was waiting there ,
so he kept on telling the other actor , for eight hours ,
how terrible the shooting of The Bird People in China had been .
So , when I told the actor , " I 'm so sorry we made you wait , " "
he said , " No problem . Thanks to The Bird People in China , I didn 't get bored . "
He was able to talk about it for eight hours .
It must have been tough for the listener , actually .
Had you worked with him , Tengan ?
No , I hadn 't .
This is so confusing .
But we feel something from him . He is awesome .
Let 's talk about the scenes coming up .
It relates to the story .
I think she had experienced some trauma in her childhood ,
and it became this huge part of her . Her love became obsession .
That 's how I look at it .
Her only way of showing love was through torture ,
since she had been tortured when she was a kid
by the Reniji Ishibashi character .
She thought they were the same thing .
That 's why she tortured people she loved as an expression of love .
Yeah , that 's one way to look at it .
She may have some other reasons .
Like ...
I can say that you 're right about her craziness
growing out of the nature of events that happened in her past .
I think those things had an impact on her in very special ways .
To play a role , actors usually ask lots of questions ,
and they try to better understand the character .
But she felt intuitively that she knew how to play this role .
We didn 't ask how she interpreted it , because we liked it that way
and we wanted to hold on to the mystery .
We didn 't force our image of the character on her .
Usually we 're supposed to understand all of the characters in a film .
That 's the director 's job
and the assistant director 's job , I 've been told that all my life .
" You need to understand your characters .
" Use your understanding to direct them . "
But , in this case , I didn 't understand ,
and I couldn 't pretend that I did .
So , when we were not sure about something , we asked Asami .
That 's what we did . It didn 't always clear up our questions .
Even if we got an answer , we couldn 't tell if it was true or not .
Come to think of it , this seems to happen to me a lot .
The idea of cause and effect
Is , of course , easy to understand , and it 's very useful ,
but there are things that are unbelievable .
The past Asami talks about sounds a little different
from what the real story must be .
So ... well ...
Look , Miike visualized something as disgusting as this .
I wrote it , but I wondered if you would actually shoot it .
And he did . He visualizes every single line .
When I saw this scene , I realised that he shot everything .
So , it was written in the script .
Yes , it was .
But a lot of directors don 't or won 't shoot everything ,
and some will get mad if I don 't write out every little detail .
But this guy shoots everything that 's in the script .
Did that make you happy ?
Well ... I 'm not sure .
I felt , sometimes , that I could have written some parts better .
But I didn 't feel like there was anything unnecessary .
The director of photography was Hideo Yamamoto , right ?
Yes .
Had you worked with him before ?
When I was making " V-Cinema "
and I was an assistant director ,
he did a lot of work on set , mostly as a camera assistant .
Unlike in America , we have to climb up the career ladder .
The person in the lowest position loads film ,
then starts pulling focus after learning some stuff , then adjusts apertures ,
then becomes chief , then finally becomes a camera operator .
That 's how the Japanese film industry works .
And I was the third assistant director , and doing slating .
Then I was the second , then chief , then finally I became a director .
In the camera department , the climb to the top is a bit faster ,
but it 's close , it 's almost the same .
I think we went to the same school , too .
- Right . - Yokohama .
I think we were in the same year or something .
I knew his name .
But you didn 't meet until you were both on the set .
Right . We met when we were still assistants .
One day , we were going , " Wow , we came all that way . "
But it 's not like ...
we were best friends or anything .
We eat together sometimes , but we don 't know each other real well .
We 're not aware of each other 's personal lives .
When I want to respect someone ...
I want to keep a good image of them in my head ,
and I think knowing them too well can be detrimental to the work .
The more we just work together ,
the further my image probably goes away from the reality , I imagine .
But he 's very flexible .
He has some hang-up about death .
Yamamoto shot one of Takeshi Kitano 's films .
It was Fireworks .
His films are very different .
He almost died once . It might 've been an attempted suicide .
But he recovered and started shooting films .
So , he had a near-death experience .
What 's interesting about Hideo Yamamoto is ... he prays .
His father and mother both died early on in his life .
She died right after he was born .
None of his relatives are living ,
so I think he thought that when he got to be his parents ' age , he 'd die .
He could 've been thinking that since he was a kid .
It 's natural . He 's tried to forget it , but can 't .
That 's who he is .
So , whatever life he 's led past that age has been like extra time .
He 's okay , too , he 's very healthy .
But that 's not something anyone can just learn .
You can 't create that in the frame
or in the lighting .
But how he lives definitely shows in the picture ,
no matter what he shoots , it shows right there .
For me , it had to be Hideo Yamamoto .
He doesn 't want to do anything eccentric .
He doesn 't try to make a good picture .
He regrets it when he makes a good picture .
He likes simple shooting .
I don 't think he likes being told , " That was a great picture . "
I think he likes making a good film , not creating a good picture .
I really appreciate that approach .
So , do you work with him often ?
Yes , we do .
We did Yatterman together .
That had nothing to do with death , though .
I heard you had a promotional tour for Audition .
Was that in 2001 ?
Right .
And then 9 / 11 happened .
Right , it was the same time .
We were planning to attend a film festival in Toronto .
We were going to do a promotion for / chi the Killer .
The promotion came with barf bags .
It was this big event where the audience received barf bags .
Anyway , we were going to go over there for this promotion .
Right before that , it was going to be released in Los Angeles .
So , we stopped off in Los Angeles for this other promotion .
We went to Los Angeles and promoted our film ,
and on the day we were going to fly to Toronto ,
we found out something terrible had happened in New York .
Of course , our flight was cancelled , and we couldn 't go to Toronto .
They were wondering if they should even continue the festival .
They decided to continue with it , to show that the terrorists had not won .
I thought that was great .
We were going to go back to Japan on a flight out of San Francisco .
So , as we 're driving from Los Angeles to San Francisco ,
we found out Dead or Alive was going to be released that same day .
They invited us to come and promote that ,
so we showed up and did an audience meet-and-greet .
That was a strange series of experiences .
It 's totally off-topic ,
but Imamura 's last work was September 11 ,
and Tengan wrote the screenplay .
I guess you guys made the film together , right ?
When I heard about the project ...
I thought it would be great . I thought it was a great idea .
It was something inevitable .
Imamura wasn 't expecting anything like that .
Right . The project was brought to him .
But he really felt something for it , and decided to accept it .
This was great . Tomorowo Taguchi was incredible .
It was an almost inhuman performance .
I think that film is a masterpiece .
And you wrote the screenplay , Tengan ?
Yes . One of the stories .
And they brought the project to you ?
Yeah , yeah .
It was 11 directors from around the world all working together on one movie .
And the theme was the attacks ?
No , it wasn 't .
There was this piece of Chinese poetry .
A author named Masuji Ibuse had translated it ,
and Imamura added one line to the end .
He wanted to make a film out of this poem .
He wanted to do it with Ken Ogata ,
and he left the story part to me .
He was like , " I want to shoot this . The story is up to you . "
You can 't tell who this guy is . Even Japanese people can 't tell .
We talked about Fireworks , which was shot by Yamamoto ,
and this guy was the main character in that .
The movie received the Golden Lion at the Venice Film Festival .
His name is Ren Osugi .
He 's received all kinds of awards for best actor in Japan .
When he eats vomit , he says , " Yummy . "
He is also a " toy " type , like Ishibashi .
Could you believe it when he accepted this role ?
Well ... many actors are actually ...
not very happy about the roles they usually get .
The more popular they become , the more likable roles they have to play .
They get typecast as these likable guys , even when they 're bad guys .
And when it 's a good guy everybody has to feel sympathy for him .
Most actors are outlaws .
Many of them feel like , " I didn 't become an actor to say this stupid line . "
I think he really wanted to play this kind of role .
This is so terrible . He 's only wearing briefs .
This was the special makeup scene , right ?
We talked about the eight hours , right ?
This was the scene they waited for .
The guy in the bag , Ren Osugi , he was the listener .
That 's a scarier situation than the story in the movie .
How frightening .
The frustration exploded in the form of great acting ,
and that made the movie scarier .
Somewhere around here , as Tengan talked about before ,
the story starts going back and forth in time .
There was order up until this point , but now it 's starting to get messed up .
The characters start losing control .
Directing these scenes , it 's like something was driving me .
We couldn 't discuss it too much .
The story made sense to us somehow ,
and we didn 't want to change that feeling .
Did you shoot the scenes in the order they were scripted ?
In order ? There 's no way to shoot in order .
We have to shoot everything for each set one set at a time .
It gets all out of order , but that 's inevitable .
It 's inconvenient , but there are also good things about it .
We have control over the movie .
It gives us a measure of control over the actors .
If they don 't follow instructions , there will be continuity problems .
So , I can keep my film under control . For the most part .
Oh , the scene where he gets killed .
She looks very happy for some reason .
Cutting meat . Just cutting meat here .
For the last scene ...
the sound guy , Kenji Shibazaki , did a really good job .
He 's done most of my films ,
and he 's probably done half of all Japanese films , really .
Yeah , most of my films , too .
He 's a really strange guy .
Like a little boy sometimes .
He makes weird sounds and noises that other people can 't make .
He was in the studio for a long time for this scene .
The scene was like this , she 's cutting through flesh ,
and she 's cutting into a big bone with this wire .
And he was trying really hard
to create the sound of the moment the wire finally reaches the bone .
The sound changes when it reaches the bone .
He put all his efforts into that scene .
If his parents saw how he worked , I bet they 'd have ... mixed feelings .
When I saw him right after Imprint ,
as soon as he saw my face , he was like , " Was that okay ? "
I went , " I don 't know . "
This whole bit , this scene ...
It was a little different from the original story .
What really struck me , what stayed with me
was the simplicity of each character in such crazy situations .
Things get really messed up , but they 're still simple people .
She changes her clothes , she follows the right steps .
Things go back and forth in time .
But she handles the simple process of cutting legs with no problem .
It 's not an illusion , it happens for real .
There was a contrast .
And I felt scared when I was reading it .
How did you feel when you were writing ?
I wrote in a bit of an elevated mood ,
but when you see it visually , it suddenly has become real .
That 's the power of visuals . When I see it , it makes me feel sick .
It 's started .
From this moment on , Ishibashi can 't act anymore .
She injects him with something . All he can do is move his hands .
And groan . He can just groan .
I think he had concerns about how long he had to be like that .
When we started shooting ,
he was a little concerned ,
but as it goes , Asami made him feel like he could do anything .
So , he was willing to move just his hands .
Of course , he 's an actor and he 's acting ,
but all his tricks and tools as an actor have been taken away from him here .
But he 's the main character . He has to be there .
Shiina never asked ...
why Asami was doing this .
But she looks most beautiful in this scene for some reason .
It 's interesting . Oh , he is moving his hand .
Did you have a special way of shooting this ?
No , nothing out of the ordinary .
But ... you know ...
this may sound strange , but the atmosphere on the set ...
is kind of gentle and calm for violent scenes .
It 's filled with love .
When they fight , the punches can 't hit anyone .
But it has to look like they hit . For this scene , it has to look painful .
And it accelerates .
That 's cruel .
She really looks like she 's going to go " Kiri-kiri-kiri " in that cute way .
What she 's doing is horrible , though .
She can 't help doing this , and that feeling shows on her face .
She kind of looks happy .
I think this scene turned out to be pretty great .
Casting was great .
If it wasn 't her ...
- It would 've been different . - I think so .
She is not trying to show who she is .
She doesn 't have any intention of doing that .
It looks like it took a long time to shoot this .
We try not to take too long to do these kinds of scenes .
I mean ...
Of course , it took more than one day .
For instance , in regular scenes , we 'll break on normal schedules ,
but we can 't just break for an hour in the middle of a painful scene .
Even if it 's a little rough , we have to keep moving .
Our camera guy wanted to add one more light here ,
but he knows the priority is the actors , not the lighting .
I don 't have to say that . He already knows .
In that way , we keep on going without losing the tension .
Of course , we shoot till very late at night .
You know , when you were a kid ,
and you were really tired at night ,
wasn 't it fun to stay awake just because your parents had told you not to ?
We 'd all start feeling excited after 2 : 00 in the morning .
We 're all used to being on the set ,
but it suddenly becomes something like a fun event .
We shoot scenes with some special makeup on one day ,
and move on to the next day .
Or we take a few hours ' break and move on to the next scene .
There 's no other way to do it .
There 's a consistency to her . She always has it .
Here 's where she starts cutting his legs .
This scene seemed to have had an influence on Hollywood movies .
The impact of the scene was so strong .
Yeah , Eli Roth .
Right . Hostel was the example .
They really love horror movies ,
so this ended up being one of their favorites .
It didn 't start with this movie . There were others before it .
But from their point of view , they really enjoyed it , I guess .
I wonder if there 's anyone else in America besides Eli Roth
who will listen to this commentary .
He might be watching this with Tarantino .
It 's difficult to imagine
what kind of person would listen to this .
But if it 's Eli , I can imagine that .
Can you hear me , Eli ?
Can you hear me ? Can you hear me , Tarantino ?
This scene ...
She 's always the same .
I know it 's a movie , but she 's been acting crazy for a while .
And she always had this way of making it all appear normal , you know ?
In this sequence , for example , where she puts liquid in a syringe .
She just does it as if it 's something she does all the time in real life .
Oh , no ... That 's bad .
The sound effects were great in this . The sound of the cutting .
She 's smiling innocently .
- That looks incredible . - It 's classic .
This was great .
How was the special makeup done for this scene ?
Matsui did the makeup . I work with him a lot .
He 's weird , too . It 's like his life wears special makeup .
But he 's wonderful .
We offered him this gig with very little time or budget ,
but he doesn 't think about that stuff , he just concentrates on doing his best .
I heard that in Japan and some other countries ,
sometimes people would walk out because of this scene .
Yeah , there were always some at the festivals .
Some people came without knowing what kind of movie it was .
They thought it was about an audition .
There were some who couldn 't take it even if they knew what it was about .
One time , I was at a festival and I was watching it with an audience ,
and this person walked up to me and said , " You 're sick . " "
In English , of course . She had to say that to me .
When she left , the audience around me started clapping .
They were like , " She left ! You 're sick !
1 " - You 're sick ! You 're one of us ! "
They were like that .
I think it 's natural to have different reactions .
When we sit in the dark , we have our own preferences .
We have our own favourites .
But there is a tendency to try to make films
that everybody can enjoy and cry together over .
To me , that 's unnatural .
I went through all kinds of criticism at many different festivals ,
and I think ...
We should all make different movies . That 's the way to go .
In that sense , this movie was very successful ...
since you got such a variety of reactions .
I think the audience 's feelings and reactions are stronger in a theatre .
It 's scary to watch my own films with audiences .
When it 's for foreigners , I don 't know how it 's being translated or conveyed .
Some folks get mad , but others enjoy it a lot .
The reactions of the audience are always diverse .
It 's completely different at each and every festival .
You can feel it right there .
That 's one reason I find my job as a director so fascinating .
Have you watched your films with theatre audiences ?
Yes .
- It 's not comfortable . - It 's uncomfortable .
Yeah , it makes me very restless ,
and I feel that way whether they like it or not .
I would probably feel better if someone told me , " You 're sick . "
I really was scolded by this middle-aged lady .
That 's funny .
In Hollywood , they love remakes . They love to remake old movies .
Several Japanese horror movies have been remade in America and other places .
Have you received any offers like that ?
Yes , I have , frequently .
Over there ...
they don 't want to miss anything they see as having potential .
But it 's about timing .
Good timing or bad timing .
And I think , for this film ...
I think it matches the story to have Asian characters .
If they were to remake this film in America ,
it could become something completely different .
There she goes .
Have you had offers to direct movies in other countries ?
Yes .
Do you have any plans to do something like that ?
Oh , definitely . It depends on my schedule .
For one thing ...
I think ...
the pay would be much better than it is in Japan .
But we have different philosophies about filmmaking schedules and time .
Going over there would be like selling one or two years ' worth of my time .
I just can 't get used to the idea .
We 've negotiated but not agreed , and the projects fade away .
Do you mean that you have to start committing your time
once you 've accepted a project , even before shooting begins ?
I just feel scared that my freedom will be taken away .
Also , it looks tough . A lot of people are watching you in Hollywood .
You have to show rushes to the guys in suits .
And I like the privilege of final cut .
So , I 'm just not sure if that 's where I want to go as a director .
So , 10 years have passed .
Time flies .
When you see this film that you made 10 years ago ,
do you have a different impression than you did before ?
What do you think ?
It 's well-balanced in certain ways .
I think there was a good balance among the actors , the crew ,
the director and me .
That had to help .
If there wasn 't a good balance , it would have turned out differently .
I think there are things you can make only at certain times .
I don 't have any complaints watching it now .
It does feel a little like watching somebody else 's film
when I see something I did 10 years ago .
But it 's precious .
I don 't want to change anything . I have no intention of changing it .
Can you tell me what Audition meant to you ,
as a director , when you think about your career ?
And Tengan , when you think about how your screenplay works ,
what does Audition mean to you ? Can you tell me ?
I 'm just glad that people other than Japanese movie fans
have watched this film , people from all over the world .
Cult movie fans .
We rented a regular house , we shot it in Japan ,
and it was accepted the world over just as it was .
I really feel that ...
there are a lot of things I can do in Japan .
I don 't have to leave Japan to do a big film that finds an audience .
When I go overseas and tell people I wrote Audition ...
some people get so excited .
It reminds me that so many people ...
from all different places have seen it .
I think the film has a power , and that 's led to it being so recognised .
I feel incredibly lucky to have been involved in it at all .
All right . Thank you both so much .
And remember , we 're working together again on our new project .
I 'm not sure what 's going to happen .
It will be allowed to be shown .
It better be !